Guide to the Harold John Lutz Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Harold John Lutz papers
1914-1997
MS 1723
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.25
(3 boxes)
The papers include correspondence, notes, and photographs which document Harold John Lutz's scholarly interests in the field of forestry, primarily soil science, ecology, and forest lands in Alaska.
Lutz, H. J. (Harold John), 1900-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lauralee A. Lutz, 1997-1998.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Harold John Lutz was born in Saline, Michigan, on August 11, 1900. He received his undergraduate education at Michigan State University and completed his master's degree and Ph.D. in forestry at Yale University in 1927 and 1933 respectively. Early in his career he worked for the United States Forest Service in Alaska and taught forestry at Penn State College. He joined the faculty of the Yale School of Forestry in 1933, where he taught until his retirement in 1968. He was a pioneer in the field of forest soils. Lutz died in 1991.
Scope and Contents
The papers include correspondence, notes, and photographs which document Harold John Lutz's scholarly interests in the field of forestry, primarily soil science, ecology, and forest lands in Alaska.
Ecology; Forest fires -- Alaska; Forest soils; Forests and forestry; Soil science; Photographs; Ball, Carleton R. (Carleton Roy), 1873-1958; Chandler, Robert F. (Robert Flint), 1907-; Leopold, A. Starker (Aldo Starker), 1913-1983; Lutz, H. J. (Harold John), 1900-; Wieland, G. R. (George Reber), 1865-1953; Yale University. School of Forestry
- Original accession, Accession 1997-M-115
  - General
    - Biographical and bibliographic information, Circa 1933-1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - McCormick, John [re phytographs], 1964-1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - United States Forest Service [photographs], 1921-1923 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Weigle, W. G. [includes his manuscript for "National Forest Administration in Alaska Prior to 1920"], 1953 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Yale University [includes letters of congratulation on appointments], 1932-1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Publication files
    - 1928: "Trends and Silvicultural Significance of Upland Forest Succession in Southern New England", 1928-1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1929: "Natural Climax Forest Communities and Exotic Trees", 1929-1940 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1930
      - "Original Forest Composition in Northwestern Pennsylvania as Indicated by Early Land Survey Notes", 1930-1935 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - "The Vegetation of Hearts Content, a Virgin Forest in Northwestern Pennsylvania", 1929-1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - "Observations of the Invasion of Newly Formed Glacial Moraines by Trees", 1929-1930, 1953, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - "A New Species of Cupressimoxylon...", 1928-1930 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - "Effect of Cattle Grazing on Vegetation of a Virgin Forest in Northwestern Pennsylvania", 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1931
      - "The Relation of Forest Composition and Rate of Growth to Certain Soil Characteristics", 1930-1934 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - "Technic of Preparing Thick Sections of Mature Pine Cones", 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 1932
      - "Relation of Forest Site Quality to Number of Plant Individuals per Unit Area", 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - "Notes on Plant Indicators of Mull Forest Soil in Northwestern Pennsylvania", 1931-1933 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 1934
      - "Ecological Relations in the Pitch Pine Plains of Southern New Jersey", 1928-1988 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - "Concerning a Geological Explanation of the Pine Barrens", 1933-1935, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - 1935: "Origin of White Pine...and Basal Branch Features" (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - 1936: "Scars Resulting from Glaze on Woody Stems", 1935-1940 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - 1937: "The Influence of Soil Profile Horizons on Root Distribution...", 1937-1974 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - 1939: "The Influence of Tree Roots on Soil Morphology", 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - 1940: "Disturbance of Forest Soil Resulting from the Uprooting of Trees", 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - 1941
      - "The Nature and Origin of Layers of Fine-Textured Material in Sand Dunes", 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - "Vertical Distribution of Heavy Minerals in Virgin and Cultivated Soils", 1941 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - 1943: "Establishment, Development, and Management of Conifer...Connecticut", 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - 1944
      - "Injuries to Young Tree Trunks from Antler Rubbing by Deer", 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - "Determination of Certain Physical Properties of Forest Soils", 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - 1945: "Soil Conditions of Picnic Grounds in Public Forest Parks", 1957-1963 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - 1946: Forest Soils
      - Correspondence, 1941-1966 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - Publicity and reviews, 1946-1950 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - 1951
      - "Ecological Effects of Forest Fires in the Interior of Alaska", 1951-1973 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - "The Concentration of Certain Chemical Elements in the Soils of Alaska Archaeological Sites", 1950-1974 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - 1952: "Occurrence of Clefts in the Wood of Living White Spruce in Alaska", 1950-1951, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - 1958
      - "Vegetation and Topographic Situation as Indicators of Forest Land Classes in Air-photo Interpretation of the Alaska Interior", 1956-1962 (Box 2, Folder 35)
      - "Geology and Soil in Relation to Forest Vegetation", 1935-1981 (Box 2, Folder 36)
      - "Observation on Diamond Willow with Particular Reference to Its Occurrence in Alaska", 1951-1971 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - 1959: "Aboriginal Man and White Man as Historical Causes of Fires in the Boreal Forest of Alaska", 1952-1964 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - 1960
      - "Fire as an Ecological Factor in the Boreal Forest of Alaska", 1955-1961 (Box 2, Folder 39)
      - "History of the Early Occurrence of Moose on the Kenai Peninsula...Alaska", 1952-1964 (Box 2, Folder 40)
      - 1963: History of Sitka Spruce Planted in 1805 at Unalaska Island by the Russians", 1985-1989 (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Additional materials, 1914-1997; Accession 1998-M-112
  - Biographical sketches and other biographical material, 1957-1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1924-1982 (Box 1, Folder 2 - 6)
  - Diaries, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Speech, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Topical files
    - Alaskan forests, 1947-1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Alaskan timber surveys, 1925-1932 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Graves, Henry Solon, 1914, 1930-1951 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Kenai journal, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Spurr, Stephen H., 1941-1963, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Yale University, 1932-1965 (Box 1, Folder 14)